Guide to the Abbott Simon Papers TAM.346
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Abbott Simon Papers
1932-2002
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Simon, Abbott, 1916-
Simon, Abigail
TAM.346
3 Linear Feet in 3 record cartons and 5 folders
Abbott Simon, Esq., (1916-) was an activist in the American Student Union and chair of the American Youth Congress, in which capacity he met and corresponded with Eleanor Roosevelt. Simon was a peace activist in the latter 1940s and early 1950s, serving as executive director of the Peace Information Center, and also occupied a leadership position in the American Peace Crusade, both of which were chaired by W.E.B. Du Bois and opposed U.S. involvement in the Korean War. Simon also served on the board of the W.E.B. Du Bois Foundation. He later assisted Freda Diamond (1905-1998) in her dispute with Paul Robeson biographer Martin Duberman regarding her relationship to Robeson. The collection contains correspondence, including that with Shirley Graham Dubois, W.E.B. Dubois, and Eleanor Roosevelt; correspondence and other materials relating to Simon's military service during World War II; minutes, circulars, and other internal documents of the Peace Information Center, as well as documents of the American Student Union and the American Youth Congress, proceedings of the World Peace Congress (Washington, D.C., 1946); files relating to a 1964 Carnegie Hall memorial for W.E.B. Dubois, and for other projects relating to Du Bois's commemoration; and galleys and other materials relating to the disputes of Freda Diamond and Paul Robeson Jr. with Martin Duberman regarding his biography, Paul Robeson.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Abigail Simon in 2005. Two folders of biographical materials related to Richard Morford were added to this collection in 2006. The accession number associated with this collection are 2005.005, 2005.012, 2006.027, and NPA.2006.043.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
Historical/Biographical Note
Abbott Simon, Esq., was an activist in the American Student Union and chair of the American Youth Congress, in which capacity he met and corresponded with Eleanor Roosevelt. Simon was a peace activist in the latter 1940s and early 1950s, serving as executive director of the Peace Information Center and occupying a leadership position in the American Peace Crusade. Both organizations were chaired by W.E.B. Du Bois and opposed U.S. involvement in the Korean War. Simon later held a leadership role in the National Committee to Defend Dr. W.E.B. Du Bois and Associates, which was formed when Du Bois was charged with failing to register the Peace Information Center with the federal government. Simon also served on the board of the W.E.B. Du Bois Foundation. He later assisted Freda Diamond (1905-1998) in her dispute with Paul Robeson biographer Martin Duberman regarding her relationship to Robeson.
Related Archival Materials at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Archives
American Youth Congress Records (TAM 553)
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains correspondence, including that with Lloyd L. Brown, Angie Dickerson, Shirley Graham Du Bois, W.E.B. Du Bois, Esther Cooper Jackson, Howard (Stretch) Johnson, and Eleanor Roosevelt; correspondence and other materials relating to Simon's military service during World War II; minutes, circulars, and other internal documents of the Peace Information Center, as well as documents of the American Student Union and the American Youth Congress; proceedings of the World Peace Congress (Washington, D.C., 1946); files relating to a 1964 Carnegie Hall memorial for W.E.B. Du Bois, and for other projects relating to Du Bois's commemoration and to the custody and publication of his papers, including correspondence with Du Bois biographer David Levering Lewis; galleys and other materials relating to the disputes of Freda Diamond and Paul Robeson Jr. with Martin Duberman regarding his biography, Paul Robeson; and the typescript of an unpublished article by Simon, "No Basis for Hitler in the Factories."
Clippings (information artifacts); Manuscripts for publication.; Correspondence.; Freedom of speech -- United States.; Proceedings.; Printed ephemera.; Student movements -- United States.; Photographs.; Youth movements -- United States.; Peace movements -- United States.; Korean War, 1950-1953 |x Protest movements.; African American communists.; Communism -- United States.; Programs (documents); Duberman, Martin B.; Simon, Abbott, 1916-; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962; American Peace Crusade; Lewis, David L.; National Committee to Defend Dr. W.E.B. Du Bois and Associates in the Peace Information Center; Jackson, Esther Cooper; American Student Union; Robeson, Paul, 1898-1976; World Peace Congress; Diamond, Freda; World Peace Council; Peace Information Center; Du Bois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963; W.E.B. Du Bois Foundation; Du Bois, Shirley Graham, 1896-1977; Brown, Lloyd L. (Lloyd Louis), 1913-2003; American Youth Congress; Simon, Abigail
- American Peace Crusade, 1951-1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- American Student Union, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- American Youth Congress, 1937-1941 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Biographical and Memorabilia, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- British Peace Committee, May 1951 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Bulletin du Comite' Italien, Mar 1951 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Business Proposals / Ventures, Mar 1953 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Button: National Committee to Reopen the Rosenberg Case, undated (Box 1)
- China Welfare Appeal, Inc., Sep 1950 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Committee for a Democratic Far Eastern Policy, Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Committee of the World Congress of the Defenders of Peace, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence: Brown, Lloyd (re Robeson), Oct 30, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence: Center for Constitutional Rights, Apr 1974-Mar 1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence: Dickerson, Angie (re William Patterson Foundation), 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence: Du Bois, Shirley Graham, Jul 1953-Mar 1976 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence: Du Bois, W.E.B., Oct 1950-Feb 1963 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Correspondence: Family, 1963-1997 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Correspondence: Jackson, Esther, 1991, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Correspondence: Johnson, Howard (Stretch), 1993 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Correspondence: Military, Mar 1943-Nov 1945 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Correspondence: Roosevelt, Eleanor, Dec 1938-May 1940 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Correspondence: Simon, Abbott, Jan 1939-Apr 2002 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Correspondence: Travis, Helen, 1993, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Diammond, Freda: re Duberman Biography of Paul Robeson, Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
- DRUM (U. Mass): re Du Bois, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Du Bois, David, 1978, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Du Bois, W.E.B.: Anniversaries, Jun 1952-Apr 2002 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Du Bois, W.E.B.: Articles about, Aug 1963-1995 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Du Bois, W.E.B.: Carnegie Hall Memorial Contract, Nov 1963-Feb 1964 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Du Bois W.E.B.: Carnegie Hall Memorial (2/23/1964) Correspondence, Oct 1963-Mar 1964, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Du Bois W.E.B.: Carnegie Hall Memorial (2/23/1964) General/Planning/Miscellaneous, Dec 1963-Sep 1993 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Du Bois, W.E.B.: Carnegie Hall Memorial Speeches, Feb 1964 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Du Bois, W.E.B.: Commemorative Stamp Sheet, Jan 1992 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Du Bois, W.E.B.: Film Project, Aug 1996-Mar 1997 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Du Bois, W.E.B.: Foundation, Apr 1963-Jun 1998 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Du Bois, W.E.B.: D.L. Lewis, Dec 1986-Jul 2002 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Du Bois, W.E.B.: Memorial Centre for Pan African Culture, Dec 1991-Aug 1992 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Du Bois, W.E.B. On the World Wide Web, Feb 1997 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Du Bois, W.E.B.: "The Passions of Alan Locke", Jun 1954 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Du Bois, W.E.B.: Photographs, 1950-1973, undated (Box Tamiment Shared A002, Folder 1)
- Du Bois, W.E.B.: Speeches, re Peace, 1900-1951 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Du Bois, W.E.B.: University of Massachusetts, Feb 1966-Feb 1976 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Du Bois, W.E.B.: University of Massachusetts, Papers, etc., Oct 1973-Sep 1980 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Emergency Civil Liberties Committee, Oct 1953 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Higbee, Mark: "W.E.B. Du Bois and the Politics of Liberation, 1917-1963" (Part One of preliminary version of PhD. dissertation), 1995 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Higbee, Mark: "W.E.B. Du Bois and the Politics of Liberation, 1917-1963" (Part Two of preliminary version of PhD. dissertation), 1995 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Hutson, Frances Aileen: Memorial Service, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Illinois Peace Assembly (American Peace Crusade), 1950-1952 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Israel, David [re Dinse], Sep 1974-Sep 1975 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Kansas City Peace Committee, Dec 1951-Jan 1952 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Lightfoot [Claude] Case, Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Lil Landau Memorial Fund, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Marcantonio, Vito: Memorial Scholarship Fund, Nov 1954-Feb 1955 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Military Service WWII, Apr 1941-Dec 1942 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Military Service: Photographs, undated (Box Tamiment Shared A002, Folder 2)
- Morford, Richard: Biographical Manuscript, 1984-1986 (Box 3)
- Moss, Elizabeth, 1890-1984: A Memorial, Jan 1984 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- National Committee to Defend Dr. W.E.B. Du Bois and Associates in the Peace Information Center, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- National Committee to Re-open the Rosenberg Case, Jun 1953-Feb 1997 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- National Committee to Repeal the McCarren Act, May 1963 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- National Delegates Assembly for Peace, Feb 1952 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- New York Labor Conference for Peace, Undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Newmark, Milton J.: "Struggle" (typescript 37 pp), Jan 1997 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Peace Activism (Korean War, Nuclear Weapons), Aug 1950-Mar 1953 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Peace Information Center, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Peace Information Center: Circulars, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Peace Information Center: Correspondence (W.E.B. Du Bois, E. Moos, etc.), 1950 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Peace Information Center: Minutes, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Peace Information Center: Organization Letters (2-11), 1950 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Peace Information Center: Press Releases, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Peace Referendum (Korean War), Undated, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Peace-Gram (Peace Information Center), May 1950-Jun 1950 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Paul Robeson Archives, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Robeson: Paul Robeson (Duberman): Corrections of Chapters 20-26 of Revised Galleys Pages with References to "Freda Galley Only", ca.1988 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Robeson: Paul Robeson (Duberman): Galleys with Freda Diamonds Corrections, Chapters 1-9, pp.1-324, ca.1988 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Robeson: Paul Robeson (Duberman): Galleys with Freda Diamond's Corrections, Chapters 22-26, Notes, etc, pp. 808-1302, ca.1988 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Robeson: Robeson: Paul Robeson (Duberman): Galleys with Freda Diamond's Corrections, Chapters 10-21, ca.1988 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Robeson: Paul Robeson (Duberman): Partial Galleys with Comments [Freda Diamond, References, etc], May 1988, Sep 1988 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Robeson: Paul Robeson (Duberman): Partial Typescript and Galleys with Comments by Simon, ca. 1988 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Robeson: Paul Robeson (Duberman): Review by Gerald Horne (Peoples Daily World), Mar 30, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Robeson: Paul Robeson (Duberman): Transcript of Duberman- Simon Interview, 43 pp., 1982 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Robeson: Paul Robeson (Duberman): Typescript Chapters 26 and 27 with Notes by an Unknown (Simon? Diamond? Other?), ca.1988 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Robeson: Paul Robeson (Duberman): Typescript (Partial) and Comments, Various, Undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Paul Robeson Foundation, Nov 1998 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Robeson, David Paul: Funeral, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Robeson, Paul: Clippings and Articles about, 1943-1984 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Robeson, Paul: Salute 1973, 1963-1976 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Robeson, Paul, Jr.: Freda Diamond, Jun 1987 (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Roosevelt Memorial in the Philippines, May 1945 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Rosenberg Case, Undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Rosenberg Case: Memorial Writings, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Rosenberg Case: Translation of Paris Discussion, Nov 1996-Jul 1997 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Rosenberg Era Art Project, Jun 1989 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Rosenberg, Michael: Guardianship, Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Rosenberg, Susan: "Celebrating the Freedom of", Feb 2001 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Stockholm Petition, 1950-1951 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Scrapbook: Personal and Political, 1932, Undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Scrapbook Photographs: Personal and Political, undated (Box Tamiment Shared A002, Folder 3)
- Simon, Abbott: Photographs, circa 1940s, 1970s, undated (Box Tamiment Shared A002, Folder 4)
- U.S. Senate: Subcommittee of the Committee on Education and Labor, S.1463 (Vocational Guidance) Including Simon Statement pp.730-end, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- VIDAS Un Drama de Postguerra en dos Actos, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Women in Prison Film Proposal, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- World Peace Appeal, Undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
- World Peace Congress, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- World Peace Congress (2nd. 1950: Warsaw, Poland), Sep 1950-Dec 1950 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- World Peace Congress (2nd. 1950: Warsaw, Poland), Nov 1950-Oct 1951 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- World Peace Congress (Washington, DC, 1946) Vol.1 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- World Peace Congress (Washington, DC 1946) Vol. 2 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- World Peace Council, Jan 1951-Jul 1952 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- World War II: Photographs, circa 1940s (Box Tamiment Shared A002, Folder 5)
- Writings: Lutheran Hymns (student paper), Undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Writings: "No Basis for Hitler in the Factories", Undated (Box 3, Folder 21)